well on this week's episode of smart
money we talk about how you can pick the
right health insurance and what are the
things that you need to do before you
select your insurance plan uh Girish n
nyak is with us Girish what are the you
know how is the procedure right how do
you select the right health insurance
plan yeah good question um there are
different kinds of individual uh
insurance plans that are available so
the first basic one which you understand
is the indemnity plan which typically
covers you when uh you are hospitalized
so your expenses during hospitalization
are covered by uh the plan there are
also what we call the benefit plans so
uh this kind of gives you a fixed payout
uh if you contract a certain illness
like for example a cancer benefit if you
contract cancer it'll pay out a lumpsum
amount which you take the insurance for
without going into whether you take the
treatment or not that's not uh but in in
the previous case in Indemnity uh you
have to actually get hospitalized and
take the treatment it is reimbursing
your actual costs there's also personal
accident policies which cover uh uh you
against accidents and all so that's uh
the different kinds of health plans you
there the other uh aspect which is a
good one uh for typically need a
Indemnity plan definitely okay you
definitely need aity plans are mostly
Indemnity plans corporate plans are
mostly Indemnity plans uh which cover
you for hospitalization now plans also
come with multiple you as a family uh
you can also purchase a what is called a
floater because uh when you take an
individual plan uh say you take a 10
lakh plan for an individual then it
covers you for a 10 lakh but if you're a
family of for two adults two children
you can cover the entire family on a
floater for 10 lakhs then any one of
them incurring expenses of up to 10 lakh
is covered the total uh family incurring
expens of up to 10 lakh is covered so it
need not be any one of them can incur
the expense it's cover so one year
someone can uh incur the expense other
year other one can multiple people can
incur the expense within the as long as
total is about 10 lakhs okay I have a
question here you earlier said that a
corporate plan U is a lot of generous
corporate sort of include your parents
also in the plan right but what happens
when if and when you leave the job uh to
your parents I mean you can take a
separate plan but largely these
individual plans don't include parents
who are above the age of 60 so what
happens then how do you uh safeguard
that so you have senior citizens plans
also okay so a lot of uh insurers have
uh plans for which cover senior citizens
of course the premium is a bit higher
out there uh naturally but uh that's
something that is available okay so uh
you can use a senior citizen plan to
cover uh parents again like I said
there's also a tax angle to it because
you cover your parents and uh up to
50,000 of Premium you can set off in
your taxes taxes okay and how do I
settle my insurance claims that is you
know because there's cash list there is
reimbursement uh a lot of corporates
have cashless uh Insurance processes as
well uh but what is the process like so
typically uh the cashless process works
for both corporate as well as individual
uh insurance claims so if the typically
if the hospital is within the insurer's
network then you can go to the hospital
and uh there'll be a TPA desk out there
where you given your papers and the uh
cashless approval is given by the
insurer and based on that the hospital
treats you without you having to pay out
any uh some up some from your pocket but
if that is not available you can also go
into reimbursement which is basically
you make the payment and then give the
bills to your insurer to reimburse you
for the cost your in card uh cash L is
always better because you don't have to
Shell out anything from your pocket and
this and uh some insur I me we we are
definitely offering a anywhere cashless
facility which is basically even if the
the hospital is not within our Network
so our network is about 7,500 hospitals
but uh even if the hospital is not
within our network if you intimate us 48
hours prior to your hospitalization then
we can arrange a cash Less in that
hospital as well okay so that's a that's
a great benefit to uh to be associated
with a bigger brand like ICS lomard got
at industry level now we are having this
initiative where everyone is trying to
move to a cash lless anywhere that
should be out soon but we we already had
have had it for uh almost a year now so
you don't have that stress of you know
oh there's only a certain amount of
hospitals in your list where you have to
sort of you know go and get your
treatment or else you won't get cash so
all that is going to be uh sorted out
yeah once we have this uh cashless
anywhere cashless anywhere okay I want
to understand different scenarios right
just real life examples if I'm a 25y old
if I'm a 33y old I'm a 40y old what is
the kind of insurance that I need so
let's start with the age of 25 in that
age group uh how much Insurance do I
need how much cover do I need
yeah we have a yeah typically uh uh 25y
old I'm assuming single uh just started
off on the job uh would 7 and a half
lakh uh insurance would be good enough
of course there are tax benefits which
and that's 10,000 would be the
approximate premium including taxes uh
which one would have to pay so uh this 7
and a half lakhs you're saying is uh lar
corporate insurance has about 5 lakhs so
you're saying if someone is 25 and has a
5 lakh corporate insurance you have to
take an additional insurance or summer
short of better take insurance from uh
the beginning and what happens if you
don't claim the insurance then uh you
get a bonus which is called additional
sum insured which gets added to the uh
cover some covered every year and
depending on the insurer this could go
up to uh 50 or 100% of the sum insurance
so if you're getting covered by
corporate insurance and you're not
claiming on this uh Insurance soon this
will with the additional summon insur
this could go up to 15 lakhs on its own
okay because of the additional sum
insured okay now let's move on to
someone who's say 33 years old has maybe
just got married or is planning to have
a child right what is the kind and is a
corporate employee what is the kind of
insurance that they need yeah I say that
they would need to up their cover a bit
uh make it about uh 10 lakhs and uh
would have a floater policy covering
both self and spouse so that would be uh
better and of course you would have
add-ons because your requirements would
have increased you would have a
maternity benefit which would be uh
important again uh newborn baby cover
OPD some PL offer OPD not all insures
offer OPD because most of the individual
insurance is uh inpatient treatment that
is you need to get hospitalized but
there are plans and like we do have
plans which offer uh outpatient
treatment which is basically your
consultation your Diagnostics your
Pharmacy charges so uh you can buy OPD
add-on which covers all these uh
benefits so that is something that uh
they could cover on this okay let's move
on to the age group of say 45 to 60
right uh what is the kind of insurance
that they need and since that's an age
which is a tricky slightly tricky one uh
okay we have your 45y old businesswoman
who's married um that's a tricky one
because that's really the age when you
start developing some health issues as
well so how you plan it so like I said
plan from before but at this point in
time you typically uh say have uh couple
of kids so two adults two kids uh 25
lakh policy uh again uh is 25 laks
enough these
days I'm just giving you a base you can
always there are policies which now
offer 501 CR yeah we have now launched
uh unlimited coverage so oh really I
didn't know that okay we just launched
it okay what does that include it it's
all your everything but without a limit
for coverage okay so and so there's an
extra premium for that perhaps the
premium is U higher obviously but uh for
again for those who can afford they can
buy that coverage and it covers you
worldwide as well okay so any cost
incurred when you travel anywhere again
like I said for this uh profile You'
also need uh annual Health checkups so
if your plan offers you annual Health
checkups that should get covered because
at the age of 45 you start doing your
health your health checkups more
regularly than when you are 25 right I
know I know I understand uh so what
about retirement right there are some
people who have hit the age of 60
suddenly developing a lot of health
issues but have no insurance so what do
they do we have here a 59y old pensioner
has pre-existing medical conditions
perhaps diabetes some even have critical
illnesses like cancer Etc so what do
they do if they don't have insurance
yeah so typically it's very difficult if
you have developed a critical inness
like cancer to get a policy okay um
because that is is uh what we call a
non- insurable risk uh as but if you
have diabetes if you have hypertension
there are policies that you can get the
premium will be higher and again as a
good practice again it's always better
to declare your pre-existing illness to
the insurer before taking the policy
okay that's a i a lot of people uh
undergo stress at time of claims because
they have not declared or they forgotten
to uh mention any pre-existing ill and
diabetes and hypertension are the most
common ones that fall into this category
someone doesn't mention that uh he or
she has had diabetes when uh getting or
has hypertension and getting the policy
when it gets found out during a claim
the claim gets rejected and you have
these other issues that turn up so it's
always better to declare upfront uh
because there'll be some loading on the
premium but you'll get the policy so for
uh a uh person who's retired without a
policy you would require a cover which
typically again has annual checkups you
would add the Outpatient Treatment op P
because there would be a lot of um at
that age you would necessarily need to
see the doctor much more often than you
see at a younger age so that's a kind of
policy you would take with about 15 lakh
cover at least and a floater again for
self and spouse and that would be in the
range of about say 50,000 okay okay one
final question then um a lot of people
get sold ulips right so I mean I know
it's a very tricky topic but just
demystify it for us should people go for
your lips or not see I I am strictly
against it because I believe that your
investment should be absolutely separate
from your insurance perfect that's the
right way to look at it and that's a
life insurance uh link policy of course
of health is health is separate health
is sold without a yeah without an
investment angle to it without it's
protection for your investment I mean
that's how you look at it but for life
insurance for term insurance say for
example you think it needs to be a
separate policy all together term is I
mean you should take a Term Policy as
well because that is important but take
a Term Policy it's it's simple Insurance
that's uh that's that's so no to you
lips again investment and protection
should be separate okay that's what you
believe that's again uh to make it more
simple that that would be a but Health
we don't have that uh it's it's purely
protection uh look at it as protection
for your Investments and for your health
yeah okay all right gir thanks a lot for
joining in appreciate you taking the
time out and speaking to NBC TV8 with
that it's a wrap on Smart money thanks a
lot for
watching